Every day, I listen to harrowing stories of people fleeing for their lives,
كل يوم استمع الى قصص مروعة عن اناس يفرون لأجل النجاة بحياتهم
across dangerous borders and unfriendly seas.
عبر الحدود الخطرة والبحار الهائجة
But there's one story that keeps me awake at night,
لكن هناك قصة واحدة تؤرقني طوال الليل
and it's about Doaa.
إنها عن "دعاء"،
A Syrian refugee, 19 years old,
لاجئة سورية ،عمرها 19 عاماً
she was living a grinding existence in Egypt working day wages.
كانت تعيش حياة طاحنة في مصر من أجل الحصول على لقمة العيش
Her dad was constantly thinking of his thriving business back in Syria
كان والدها يفكر باستمرار عن مشروعه المزدهر في سوريا
that had been blown to pieces by a bomb.
الذي تم تدميره تماماً بقنبلة
And the war that drove them there was still raging in its fourth year.
والحرب التي قادتتهم إلى هناك ما زالت مستمرة، منذ أربع سنوات
And the community that once welcomed them there
والمجتمع الذي رحب بهم هناك
had become weary of them.
اصبح قلقاً منهم
And one day, men on motorcycles tried to kidnap her.
وفي يوم، حاول بعض الاشخاص على دراجة نارية اختطافها
Once an aspiring student thinking only of her future,
سابقاً، كانت طالبة طموحة تفكر في مستقبلها فقط
now she was scared all the time.
أما الآن، فهي خائفة طوال الوقت
But she was also full of hope,
لكنها أيضاً كانت مليئة بالأمل
because she was in love with a fellow Syrian refugee named Bassem.
لأنها كانت تحب لاجئ سوري اسمه "باسم"
Bassem was also struggling in Egypt, and he said to Doaa,
كان "باسم" ايضا يعاني في مصر وقال "لدعاء" :
"Let's go to Europe; seek asylum, safety.
"لنذهب لأوروبا ونطلب اللجوء السياسي، والأمان.
I will work, you can study -- the promise of a new life."
سأعمل، وأنت ستدرسين.. سنعيش حياة جديدة أفضل"
And he asked her father for her hand in marriage.
وطلب من والدها يدها ليتزوجها.
But they knew to get to Europe they had to risk their lives,
لكنهم يعرفون أنه من أجل الوصول لأوروبا يجب عليهم المخاطرة بحياتهم
traveling across the Mediterranean Sea,
السفر عبر البحر المتوسط
putting their hands in smugglers', notorious for their cruelty.
بالاتفاق مع مهربين ذوي سمعة سيئة
And Doaa was terrified of the water.
و "دعاء" كانت مرعوبة من الماء
She always had been. She never learned to swim.
كانت كذلك دائماً لم تتعلم السباحة قط
It was August that year, and already 2,000 people had died
كان ذلك في شهر اغسطس في هذا العام وقد مات 2000 شخص من قبل
trying to cross the Mediterranean,
محاولين عبور البحر المتوسط
but Doaa knew of a friend who had made it all the way to Northern Europe,
لكن "دعاء" عرفت صديقة استطاعت الوصول لشمال اوروبا
and she thought, "Maybe we can, too."
وفكرت "ربما نستطيع الوصول "
So she asked her parents if they could go,
لذا استاذنت والديها بالذهاب
and after a painful discussion, they consented,
وبعد نقاش شاق، وافقوا
and Bassem paid his entire life savings -- 2,500 dollars each --
ودفع "باسم" كل ما كان يملك.. 2500 دولار للفرد
to the smugglers.
للمهربين
It was a Saturday morning when the call came,
كان صباح السبت عندما جاءت المكالمة
and they were taken by bus to a beach, hundreds of people on the beach.
وأُخذوا الى الشاطيء عن طريق الحافلة، يوجد مئات الناس على الشاطيء
They were taken then by small boats onto an old fishing boat,
ثم أُخذوا عن طريق قوارب صغيرة إلى قارب صيد قديم
500 of them crammed onto that boat,
500 منهم محشورون على متن القارب
300 below, [200] above.
300 بالأسفل و 500 بالأعلى
There were Syrians, Palestinians, Africans, Muslims and Christians,
كان هناك سوريون، فلسطينيون، أفارقة، مسلمون ومسيحيون
100 children, including Sandra -- little Sandra, six years old --
100 طفل من ضمنهم "ساندرا" الصغيرة التي عمرها 6 سنوات
and Masa, 18 months.
و "ماسا" التي عمرها 18 شهراً
There were families on that boat, crammed together shoulder to shoulder,
كانت هناك عائلات على هذا القارب محشورة معاً كتفاً بكتف
feet to feet.
القدم بجوار القدم
Doaa was sitting with her legs crammed up to her chest,
"دعاء" كانت جالسة وأرجلها محشورة وملاصقة لصدرها
Bassem holding her hand.
"باسم" يمسك يديها
Day two on the water, they were sick with worry
اليوم الثاني في الماء كانوا مرهقون وقلقون
and sick to their stomachs from the rough sea.
ومصابون بدوار البحر
Day three, Doaa had a premonition.
اليوم الثالث ، "دعاء" كان لديها شعور داخلي
And she said to Bassem, "I fear we're not going to make it.
وقالت "لباسم" "أخشى أننا لن ننجح،
I fear the boat is going to sink."
أخاف أن يغرق المركب".
And Bassem said to her, "Please be patient.
وقال لها "باسم" : " أرجوك كوني صبورة.
We will make it to Sweden, we will get married
سوف نصل للسويد وسنتزوج
and we will have a future."
وسيكون لنا مستقبل".
Day four, the passengers were getting agitated.
اليوم الرابع ، الركاب أصبحوا قلقين
They asked the captain, "When will we get there?"
سألوا القبطان "متى سنصل؟ "
He told them to shut up, and he insulted them.
قال لهم اخرسوا و أهانهم
He said, "In 16 hours we will reach the shores of Italy."
قال " سنصل الى سواحل إيطاليا في 16 ساعة"
They were weak and weary.
كانوا متعبين ومكتئبين
Soon they saw a boat approach -- a smaller boat, 10 men on board,
بعد قليل، شاهدوا قارباً يقترب كان صغيراً وعليه 10 رجال
who started shouting at them, hurling insults,
الذين بدأوا بالصراخ عليهم وشتمهم
throwing sticks, asking them to all disembark
يلقون العصي عليهم، يطلبون منهم جميعاً النزول من القارب
and get on this smaller, more unseaworthy boat.
والصعود على هذا القارب الأصغر الغير صالح للملاحة
The parents were terrified for their children,
الأهل كانوا خائفين بشدة على ابنائهم
and they collectively refused to disembark.
ورفضوا جميعاً النزول.
So the boat sped away in anger,
ابتعد القارب الأصغر سريعاً وبغضب
and a half an hour later, came back
وبعد نصف ساعة ، عاد ثانية
and started deliberately ramming a hole in the side of Doaa's boat,
و بدأ بتعمد احداث خرق في جوانب قارب "دعاء"
just below where she and Bassem were sitting.
حيث كانت تجلس هي و "باسم"
And she heard how they yelled,
وسمعت كيف صاحوا بصوت عال
"Let the fish eat your flesh!"
" ليأكل السمك لحومكم"
And they started laughing as the boat capsized and sank.
وبدأوا في الضحك فيما انقلب المركب وغرق
The 300 people below deck were doomed.
ال 300 شخص بالأسفل قضي عليهم.
Doaa was holding on to the side of the boat as it sank,
"دعاء" كانت متمسكة بجانب القارب وهو يغرق
and watched in horror as a small child was cut to pieces by the propeller.
وشاهدت في رعب طفل صغير قطعت المروحة جسده لأجزاء
Bassem said to her, "Please let go,
قال لها "باسم": "ارجوك اتركيه"
or you'll be swept in and the propeller will kill you, too."
وإلا سينجرف جسدك إلى المروحة وتقتلك أيضاً.
And remember -- she can't swim.
وتذَكر.. هي لا تستطيع السباحة.
But she let go and she started moving her arms and her legs,
لكنها تركته وبدات تحرك ذراعيها ورجليها
thinking, "This is swimming."
معتقدة أن "هكذا تكون السباحة"
And miraculously, Bassem found a life ring.
وحدثت معجزة، وجد "باسم" طوق نجاة.
It was one of those child's rings
كان لأحد أولئك الأطفال
that they use to play in swimming pools and on calm seas.
الذين كانوا معتادين سابقاً على اللعب به في حمامات السباحة وفي البحر الهادئ
And Doaa climbed onto the ring,
وطلعت "دعاء" على طوق النجاة
her arms and her legs dangling by the side.
ذراعيها ورجليها متدلين من الجانب.
Bassem was a good swimmer,
"باسم" كان سباحاً جيداً
so he held her hand and tread water.
لذا أمسك يدها وحرك رجليه في الماء.
Around them there were corpses.
كانت حولهم الجثث
Around 100 people survived initially,
مبدئيا نجا حوالي 100 شخص
and they started coming together in groups, praying for rescue.
وبدأوا في التجمع ، يدعون من أجل النجاة
But when a day went by and no one came,
لكن مضى يوم كامل ولم يأت أحد
some people gave up hope,
فقد بعض الاشخاص الأمل
and Doaa and Bassem watched
وشاهد " بسام " و "دعاء"
as men in the distance took their life vests off and sank into the water.
الرجال بقربهم يخلعون سترة النجاة ويغرقون في الماء
One man approached them with a small baby perched on his shoulder,
أحد الرجال اقترب منهم ومعه طفل صغير فوق كتفه
nine months old -- Malek.
"مالك" صاحب التسعة اشهر
He was holding onto a gas canister to stay afloat, and he said to them,
كان يتشبث باسطوانة غاز حتى يظل طافيا وقال لهم:
"I fear I am not going to survive.
" أخاف ألا أنجو،
I'm too weak. I don't have the courage anymore."
أنا ضعيف للغاية لم أعد امتلك العزم الكافي"
And he handed little Malek over to Bassem and to Doaa,
وسلم " مالك" الصغير لباسم و لدعاء
and they perched her onto the life ring.
ووضعوه على طوق النجاة
So now they were three, Doaa, Bassem and little Malek.
الآن أصبحوا ثلاثة، "دعاء"، "باسم" والصغير " مالك"
And let me take a pause in this story right here
ودعوني أتوقف هنا قليلاً
and ask the question:
وأسأل:
why do refugees like Doaa take these kinds of risks?
لماذا يخاطر اللاجئين مثل "دعاء" ؟
Millions of refugees are living in exile, in limbo.
ملايين من اللاجئين يعيشون في المنفى، باهمال
They're living in countries [fleeing] from a war that has been raging
يعيشون في بلدان، يفرون من بلدانهم التي قامت بها حرب
for four years.
لأربع سنوات.
Even if they wanted to return, they can't.
حتى إذا أرادوا العودة، لا يستطيعون.
Their homes, their businesses,
منازلهم ، أعمالهم،
their towns and their cities have been completely destroyed.
مدنهم و بلداتهم، تم تدميرها بالكامل.
This is a UNESCO World Heritage City,
هذه هي مدينة اليونسكو للتراث العالمي
Homs, in Syria.
حمص ، في سوريا.
So people continue to flee into neighboring countries,
لذلك يستمر الناس بالفرار للبلدان المجاورة،
and we build refugee camps for them in the desert.
ونحن نبني لهم مخيمات لاجئين في الصحراء.
Hundreds of thousands of people live in camps like these,
مئات الآلاف من الناس يعيشون في مخيمات مثل هذه.
and thousands and thousands more, millions, live in towns and cities.
و آلاف الآلاف، بل الملايين، يعيشون في المدن والبلدات.
And the communities,
ومجتمعات
the neighboring countries that once welcomed them
البلدان المجاورة التي رحبت بهم مرة
with open arms and hearts
بقلوب وأذرع مفتوحة
are overwhelmed.
أُرهِقت
There are simply not enough schools, water systems, sanitation.
ببساطة ليس هناك مدارس كافية، أنظمة صرف صحي
Even rich European countries could never handle such an influx
حتى البلاد الأوروبية الغنية لن تستطيع التعامل مع مثل هذا التدفق
without massive investment.
دون دعم ضخم.
The Syria war has driven almost four million people over the borders,
تسببت الحرب السورية بنزوح 4 ملايين شخص خارج الحدود،
but over seven million people are on the run inside the country.
لكن فوق السبعة ملايين في حالة فرار دائم داخل البلاد
That means that over half the Syrian population
وهذا يعني أن فوق نصف سكان سوريا
has been forced to flee.
أُجبروا على الفرار.
Back to those neighboring countries hosting so many.
بالعودة للبلاد المجاورة التي استضافت الكثير
They feel that the richer world has done too little to support them.
إنهم يشعرون أن العالم الأغنى ساندهم بالقليل
And days have turned into months, months into years.
وتحولت الأيام لشهور، والشهور إلى سنين.
A refugee's stay is supposed to be temporary.
من المفترض أن تكون اقامة اللاجئ مؤقتة.
Back to Doaa and Bassem in the water.
لنعود إلى "باسم " و "دعاء" في الماء.
It was their second day, and Bassem was getting very weak.
كان يومهم الثاني، وأصبح "باسم" متعباً للغاية
And now it was Doaa's turn to say to Bassem,
و أصبح الآن دور "دعاء " لتقول لباسم:
"My love, please hold on to hope, to our future. We will make it."
"حبيبي، أرجوك تمسك بالأمل، بمستقبلنا. سوف ننجح"
And he said to her,
قال لها:
"I'm sorry, my love, that I put you in this situation.
" آسف يا حبيبتي لأني وضعتك في هذا الموقف..
I have never loved anyone as much as I love you."
لم أحب أحداً مثلما أحببتك"
And he released himself into the water,
وترك نفسه للماء،
and Doaa watched as the love of her life drowned before her eyes.
وشاهدت "دعاء" حب حياتها يغرق أمام أعينها.
Later that day,
فيما بعد في ذاك اليوم،
a mother came up to Doaa with her small 18-month-old daughter, Masa.
أتت أم إلى" دعاء" ومعها ابنتها البالغة 18 شهراً، "ميساء"
This was the little girl I showed you in the picture earlier,
كانت هذه هي البنت التي عرضتها عليكم من قبل في الصور
with the life vests.
وهي ترتدي سترة النجاة.
Her older sister Sandra had just drowned,
أختها الكبرى " ساندرا" غرقت للتو
and her mother knew she had to do everything in her power
وعملت أمها كل ما تسطيع
to save her daughter.
لتنقذ ابنتها.
And she said to Doaa, "Please take this child.
وقالت لدعاء: " أرجوك خذي طفلتي
Let her be part of you. I will not survive."
اجعليها جزء منك، أنا لن أنجو".
And then she went away and drowned.
وابتعدت وغرقت.
So Doaa, the 19-year-old refugee who was terrified of the water,
"دعاء" اللاجئة ذات 19 ربيعاً التي تخاف من المياه
who couldn't swim,
ولا تستطيع السباحة
found herself in charge of two little baby kids.
وجدت نفسها مسؤولة عن طفلين صغيرين.
And they were thirsty and they were hungry and they were agitated,
وكانوا متعبين وعطشى وجائعين،
and she tried her best to amuse them,
وحاولت بأفضل ما عندها أن تسليهم
to sing to them, to say words to them from the Quran.
أن تغني لهم، أن تقرأ لهم القرآن.
Around them, the bodies were bloating and turning black.
حولهم كانت الجثث تنتفخ ويتحول لونها للأسود.
The sun was blazing during the day.
كانت الشمس ملتهبة خلال اليوم
At night, there was a cold moon and fog.
وفي الليل، كان الجو بارداً وضبابياً
It was very frightening.
كان مخيفاً للغاية.
On the fourth day in the water, this is how Doaa probably looked
في اليوم الرابع في البحر، ربما تكون هكذا بدت "دعاء"
on the ring with her two children.
على طوق ومعها طفلان.
A woman came on the fourth day and approached her
في اليوم الرابع اقتربت منها امراة
and asked her to take another child --
وطلبت منها أن تأخذ طفلاً آخر
a little boy, just four years old.
ولد صغير، عمره أربع سنوات فقط
When Doaa took the little boy and the mother drowned,
عندما أخذت "دعاء" الولد الصغير وغرقت الأم،
she said to the sobbing child,
قالت للطفل الباكي:
"She just went away to find you water and food."
"ذهبت لتحضر لك الطعام والشراب".
But his heart soon stopped,
لكن بعدها بقليل توقف قلبه،
and Doaa had to release the little boy into the water.
واضطرت "دعاء" أن تترك الولد الصغير في الماء.
Later that day,
فيما بعد في ذلك اليوم،
she looked up into the sky with hope,
نظرت للسماء بأمل
because she saw two planes crossing in the sky.
لأنها رأت طائرتين في السماء.
And she waved her arms, hoping they would see her,
ولوحت بذراعيها آملة بأن يروها
but the planes were soon gone.
لكن الطائرات اختفت سريعاً.
But that afternoon, as the sun was going down,
لكن في ذلك المساء عند غروب الشمس،
she saw a boat, a merchant vessel.
رأت سفينة تجارية.
And she said, "Please, God, let them rescue me."
وقالت: " أرجوك يا رب اجعلهم ينقذوني"
She waved her arms and she felt like she shouted for about two hours.
لوحت بذراعيها وشعرت بأنها ظلت تصرخ لساعتين
And it had become dark, but finally the searchlights found her
وأصبح الجو مظلماً، لكن أخيراً وجدتها الكشافات
and they extended a rope,
ومدوا لها حبلاً
astonished to see a woman clutching onto two babies.
مذهولين من رؤية امرأة متشبثة بطفلين.
They pulled them onto the boat, they got oxygen and blankets,
جذبوهم إلى القارب، أحضروا الأكسجين والبطانيات
and a Greek helicopter came to pick them up
وأتت طوافة يونانية لتصحبهم
and take them to the island of Crete.
وتاخذهم لجزيرة "كريت".
But Doaa looked down and asked, "What of Malek?"
لكن "دعاء" نظرت وقالت: "ماذا عن مالك؟ "
And they told her the little baby did not survive --
قالوا لها أن الطفل الصغير لم ينجو،
she drew her last breath in the boat's clinic.
لفظ آخر نفس في عيادة السفينة.
But Doaa was sure that as they had been pulled up onto the rescue boat,
لكن " دعاء" كانت متاكدة أنخ أثناء سحبهم إلى قارب النجاة
that little baby girl had been smiling.
كان الولد الصغير يبتسم.
Only 11 people survived that wreck, of the 500.
نجا 11 شخص فقط من هذا الحطام من أصل 500.
There was never an international investigation into what happened.
لم يحدث أبداً تحقيق دولي عن الحادث
There were some media reports about mass murder at sea,
كانت هناك بض التقارير الاعلامية عن القتل الجماعي في البحر
a terrible tragedy,
بعنوان "مأساة فظيعة"
but that was only for one day.
لكن كان هذا ليوم واحد فقط.
And then the news cycle moved on.
و استمرت الحياة كما هي بعد ذلك.
Meanwhile, in a pediatric hospital on Crete,
في تلك الاثناء، فى مستشفى لطب الأطفال في "كريت"
little Masa was on the edge of death.
كانت الصغيرة " ميساء" على حافة الموت
She was really dehydrated. Her kidneys were failing.
كانت شاحبة حقا وكليتيها بهما فشل.
Her glucose levels were dangerously low.
وكانت معدلات الجلوكوز منخفضة بشدة.
The doctors did everything in their medical power to save them,
فعل الأطباء كل ما باستطاعتهم طبياً لانقاذهم،
and the Greek nurses never left her side,
ولم تتركها الممرضات اليونانيات قط،
holding her, hugging her, singing her words.
يحملونها، يعانقوها، يغنون لها.
My colleagues also visited and said pretty words to her in Arabic.
وزارها أيضاً زملائي وقالوا لها كلاماً جميلاً باللغة العربية.
Amazingly, little Masa survived.
وبأعجوبة، نجت "ميساء" الصغيرة.
And soon the Greek press started reporting about the miracle baby,
وتحدثت الصافة اليونانية عن الطفلة المعجزة
who had survived four days in the water without food or anything to drink,
التي نجت لأربعة أيام في البحر دون أي طعام أو شراب،
and offers to adopt her came from all over the country.
وعروض التبني أتت من أرجاء البلاد.
And meanwhile, Doaa was in another hospital on Crete,
وفي تلك الاثناء كانت "دعاء" بمشفى آخر في "كريت"
thin, dehydrated.
شاحبة ونحيفة.
An Egyptian family took her into their home as soon as she was released.
استضافتها عائلة مصرية بمنزلها بمجرد خروجها.
And soon word went around about Doaa's survival,
وانتشرت القصة عن نجاة "دعاء"
and a phone number was published on Facebook.
ونُشر رقم هاتف على "الفيسبوك".
Messages started coming in.
بدأت الرسائل تأتي،
"Doaa, do you know what happened to my brother?
"دعاء، هل تعرفين ما حدث لأخي؟
My sister? My parents? My friends? Do you know if they survived?"
أختي؟ والداي؟ أصدقائي؟ هل تمكنوا من النجاة؟"
One of those messages said,
إحدى هذه الرسائل كان فيها:
"I believe you saved my little niece, Masa."
" أعتقد أنك انقذت ابنة أختي "ميساء".
And it had this photo.
وهذه صورتها.
This was from Masa's uncle,
كانت الرسالة من عم "ميساء"
a Syrian refugee who had made it to Sweden with his family
لاجيء سوري استطاع الوصول هو وعائلته إلى السويد
and also Masa's older sister.
ومعهم أيضاً الاخت الكبرى لميساء.
Soon, we hope, Masa will be reunited with him in Sweden,
نأمل أن يجتمع هو وميساء قريباً في السويد،
and until then, she's being cared for in a beautiful orphanage in Athens.
وهي الآن في دار رعاية في "أُثينا".
And Doaa? Well, word went around about her survival, too.
وانتشرت قصة نجاة "دعاء"،
And the media wrote about this slight woman,
وتحدث الاعلام عن هذه المراة الضعيفة،
and couldn't imagine how she could survive all this time
ولم يتخيل كيف استطاعت النجاة طوال ذلك الوقت
under such conditions in that sea,
في مثل تلك الظروف في ذلك البحر،
and still save another life.
ومع ذلك أنقذت حياة أخرى.
The Academy of Athens, one of Greece's most prestigious institutions,
" اكاديمية أثينا" واحدة من افضل المعاهد اليونانية
gave her an award of bravery,
أعطتها "وسام الشجاعة"،
and she deserves all that praise,
وهي تستحق كل ذلك المدح،
and she deserves a second chance.
وتستحق فرصة ثانية.
But she wants to still go to Sweden.
لكنها ما زالت تريد الذهاب للسويد.
She wants to reunite with her family there.
تريد أن تجتمع بعائلتها هناك.
She wants to bring her mother and her father and her younger siblings
تريد أن تحضر والدها ووالدتها وأخوانها الصغار
away from Egypt there as well,
الموجودين في مصر،
and I believe she will succeed.
واعتقد أنها ستنجح في ذلك.
She wants to become a lawyer or a politician
تريد أن تصبح محامية أو سياسية
or something that can help fight injustice.
أو أي شيء يساعد على محاربة الظلم.
She is an extraordinary survivor.
إنها ناجية مميزة.
But I have to ask:
لكن علي أن اسأل:
what if she didn't have to take that risk?
ماذا إذا كانت لم تضطر لهذه المخاطرة أساساً؟
Why did she have to go through all that?
لماذا يجب أن تمر بكل ذلك؟
Why wasn't there a legal way for her to study in Europe?
لماذا لا يوجد طريقة قانونية للدراسة في اوروبا؟
Why couldn't Masa have taken an airplane to Sweden?
لماذا لا تستطيع "ميساء" ركوب الطائرة لأوروبا ؟
Why couldn't Bassem have found work?
لماذا لم يجد "باسم" عملاً؟
Why is there no massive resettlement program for Syrian refugees,
لماذا لا يوجد برنامج ضخم لإعادة توطين اللاجئين السوريين،
the victims of the worst war of our times?
ضحايا الحرب الأسوأ في عصرنا؟
The world did this for the Vietnamese in the 1970s. Why not now?
لقد فعل العالم هذا لمواطني "فيتنام" في السبعينيات لماذا الآن لا يفعلوا المثل؟
Why is there so little investment in the neighboring countries
لماذا يوجد اسثمار قليل في البلدان المجاورة
hosting so many refugees?
التي تستضيف الكثير من اللاجئين؟
And why, the root question,
ولماذا، السؤال الجذري،
is so little being done to stop the wars, the persecution
يُفعل القليل من أجل وقف الحروب ، الاضطهاد
and the poverty that is driving so many people
والفقر الذي يقود العديد من الناس
to the shores of Europe?
لسواحل اوروبا؟
Until these issues are resolved,
لحين تُحل هذه المشاكل،
people will continue to take to the seas
سيظل الناس يلجؤون للبحر
and to seek safety and asylum.
ليطلبوا اللجوء والامان.
And what happens next?
وماذا يحدث مستقبلاً؟
Well, that is largely Europe's choice.
حسناً، هذا الاختيار معظمه لأوروبا.
And I understand the public fears.
وأنا اتفهم المخاوف الشعبية.
People are worried about their security, their economies, the changes of culture.
الناس قلقون على أمنهم، اقتصادهم، تغير الثقافة.
But is that more important than saving human lives?
لكن هل هذا أهم من انقاذ حياة بشرية؟
Because there is something fundamental here
لان هناك شيئا أساسياً هنا
that I think overrides the rest,
والذي اعتقد أنه يتخطى الباقي،
and it is about our common humanity.
وهو عن انسانيتنا.
No person fleeing war or persecution
لا شخص فارّ من الحرب أو مضطهد
should have to die crossing a sea to reach safety.
يجب أن يموت وهو يقوم بعبور البحر ليصل للأمان.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
One thing is for sure,
شيء واحد مؤكد،
that no refugee would be on those dangerous boats
أنه لن يوجد لاجئ على متن تلك القوارب الخطرة
if they could thrive where they are.
إذا كانوا يستطيعون العيش أينما كانوا.
And no migrant would take that dangerous journey
ولا يوجد مهاجر يمكن أن يسلك هذه الرحلة الخطرة
if they had enough food for themselves and their children.
إذا كان هناك طعام كاف لأنفسهم ولأطفالهم.
And no one would put their life savings
ولا يوجد شخص سيضع كل ما تبقى من ماله
in the hands of those notorious smugglers
في أيدي اولئك المهربين
if there was a legal way to migrate.
إن كان هناك طريقة شرعية للهجرة.
So on behalf of little Masa
لذلك، نيابة عن ميساء الصغيرة
and on behalf of Doaa
وعن دعاء
and of Bassem
وعن باسم
and of those 500 people who drowned with them,
ونيابة عن الـ500 شخص الذين غرقوا معهم،
can we make sure that they did not die in vain?
هل يمكن أن نضمن أن لا يكون موتهم هباءاً منسياً؟
Could we be inspired by what happened,
هل يمكن أن نُلهم بما حدث،
and take a stand for a world in which every life matters?
ونأخذ موقفاً لأجل عالم كل حياة بشرية فيه تعتبر مهمة؟
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)